Guide to the Baruch Charney Vladeck Papers and Photographs TAM.037
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series I. Correspondence, 1912-1938
  - VLADECK, B.C.-LECTURES, undated (Box 5)
    Reel 12
  - VLADECK, B.C.-SPEECHES, undated (Box 5)
  - VLADECK, B.C.-WRITINGS, undated (Box 5)
  - VLADECK, B.C.-WRITINGS, undated (Box 5)
  - VLADECK, S.C.[Sonny], undated (Box 5)
  - "W" GENERAL, undated (Box 5)
  - WEVD BROADCASTING STATION, undated (Box 5)
  - WALD, LILLIAN D., 1927-1932 (Box 6)
  - WARBURG, FELIX M., 1924-1937 (Box 6)
  - WEINREICH, MAX (Dr.), 1927-1938 (Box 6)
  - WENDROFF, undated (Box 6)
  - WORKMEN'S CIRCLE, 1912-1938 (Box 6)
  - WORKS PROGRESS ADMINISTRATION: OPA, undated (Box 6)
  - WORKS PROGRESS ADMINISTRATION: HENRY G. ALSBERG, undated (Box 6)
  - "DAS WORT" LIBRARY, undated (Box 6)
  - "Y" GENERAL, undated (Box 6)
  - "Z" GENERAL, undated (Box 6)
  - ZIONIST CONGRESS, undated (Box 6)
  - "DIE ZUKUNFT" JEWISH MONTHLY, undated (Box 6)
- Series II. General Material, 1907-1938
  This series consists of a number of unsorted boxes identified by general subject. These include: correspondence dated from 1907-1918, personal correspondence and that of other Vladeck family members, and correspondence regarding Vladeck's illness and passing. Also included in this series are several boxes of clippings and other printed materials, which have not been microfilmed.
  Content open for research without restrictions. Boxes 6-8 of this series have been microfilmed. Researchers must use microfilm where it exists.
  - VLADECK early correspondence circa 1907-1918. (Box 6)
    Reel 13
  - VLADECK, Clara Richmond. early correspondence, circa 1906-1917. (Box 6)
    Reel 14
  - Family correspondence., undated (Box 6, Box 7)
  - Correspondence re: Illness, 1938 (Box 7)
  - Condolence correspondence, 1938 (Box 7)
    Reel 15-16
  - Miscellaneous unidentified material., undated (Box 7)
    Reel 16-17
  - Financial papers, notes, etc., undated (Box 7, Box 8)
    Reel 17-19
  - Autobiography, biographical material, memorials, membership certificates etc., undated (Box 8)
    Reel 19-20
  - Newspaper Clippings-Italian (oversized) (not microfilmed) (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings-English-Funeral/Death Notices/Obituaries (Oversized) (not microfilmed) (Box Tamiment Shared XOS001, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings-English-General (Oversized) (not microfilmed) (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings-Yiddish (Oversized) (not microfilmed) (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings-Yiddish (Oversized) (not microfilmed) (Box Tamiment Shared XOS001, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings-Russian (Oversized) (not microfilmed) (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings-English-Mayor Hoan (not microfilmed), 1961 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - New York School for Nurses: Certificate (not microfilmed) (Box Tamiment Shared XOS001, Folder 3)
  - Certificates from City of New York, 1923-1932 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Bibliographic Material (not microfilmed) (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - New York City Council Calendar January-June 1938 (not microfilmed), January 1939-June1938 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Lincoln Tunnel Dedication (not microfilmed), December 21, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Vladeck Memorial Tributes (not microfilmed), 1938 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Independent News Clippings (not microfilmed), November 15, 1938 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Brooklyn Forum Academy of Music 1933-34 Season (not microfilmed), 1933-1934 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Lists of Names and Addresses (not microfilmed) (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Clippings and Essays on Jews and Arabs in Palestine (not microfilmed) (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - 'Baruch Carney Vladeck' pamphlet by John Herling (not microfilmed), 1939 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - New York City Financial Information (not microfilmed), 1937 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper Clippings-English-Funeral/Death Notices/Obituaries (not microfilmed), 1938 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Clippings-Yiddish (not microfilmed) (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings-Yiddish (not microfilmed) (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Hand-Written Notes-Russian (not microfilmed) (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Print Material- Russian (not microfilmed) (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Notes-English (not microfilmed) (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Print Material-German (not microfilmed) (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Misc. Correspondence (not microfilmed) (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Misc. Printed Material-English (not microfilmed) (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - 'Climate to Order' Document (not microfilmed) (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Material on Fascism in Europe (not microfilmed) (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Print Material-Yiddish (not microfilmed) (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Print Material-Polish (Pierwsza Krew) (not microfilmed), 1930 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Portrait drawing of Baruch Charney Vladeck (Box Shared Tamiment 045)
- Series III. Second Donation
  This series is comprised of materials received after the original donation was processed and microfilmed. It documents Vladeck's career in the Socialist and American Labor parties, as business manager of the Jewish Daily Forward, and as a leader of anti-fascist and anti-Nazi organizations. The earliest material in this series dates from soon after Vladeck's arrival in the United States. There are copies of papers he wrote while in college, early tax returns, and a few letters relating to Vladeck's brief tenure as a NYC Alderman during World War I. Most of the correspondence and subject files are devoted to the 1930s, the last decade of Vladeck's life. A small selection of correspondence and related materials of Vladeck's wife, Clara Richman Vladeck, and his daughter, May Vladeck Bromberg, are included in a family sub-series. There is also material documenting the Women's Division of the American Labor Party, in which May Bromberg was a major figure, as well as clippings and condolence letters about Vladeck's death in 1938.
  In the correspondence series are important letters to and from Daniel Hoan, Norman Thomas, Upton Sinclair, and prominent figures in the world of Jewish culture and the Jewish labor movement. This series also strongly represents Vladeck's role in the political, cultural, and charitable activities of the Forward Association and radio station WEVD. Vladeck's tenure as a member of the New York City Housing Authority is documented in Sub-series B, and his 1937 campaign for the City Council in Sub-series C. A set of clippings (mostly in English) document Vladeck's career in the Council as the majority leader of the Socialist, American Labor Party, and Republican Fusion coalition. The housing series includes files of minutes of several committees and sub-committees of the NYC Housing Authority. Included, as well, are materials about workers' housing collected from Israel, the Soviet Union, England, and Canada, as well as the United States, and a group of speeches about workers' housing in New York. A small selection of documents and clippings details the opening and construction of the Vladeck Houses, a public housing project named for Vladeck after his death.
  Series III is arranged in six sub-series: A. Correspondence; B. Housing; C. Elections; D. Subject Files; E. Family; F. Clippings.
  - Subseries A: Correspondence
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1908 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1909 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1910 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1911 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1912 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1913 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1914 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1915 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1916 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1917 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1918 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1919 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1921 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, 1922 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, 1923 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, 1924 (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1925 (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, 1926 (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, 1927 (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence, 1928 (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, 1929 (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence, 1930 (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 12, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 12, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence, Jan 1933-Aug 1933 (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence, Sep 1933-Dec 1933 (Box 12, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence, Jan 1934-Feb 1934 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, Mar 1935-Dec 1934 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, Jan 1935-Feb 1935 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, Mar 1935-Apr 1935 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, May 1935-Sep 1935 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, Oct 1935-Nov 1935 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, Dec 1935 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, Jan 1936-Mar 1936 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, Apr 1936 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, May 1936-Jul 1936 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, Aug 1936-Sep 1936 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, Oct 1936 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, Nov 1936 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, Dec 1936 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1937-1938 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Subseries B: Housing
    - Housing: General, 1934-1936 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - New York Housing Authority (NYCHA): General, 1934-1935 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - NYCHA: Minutes, 1934-1935 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - NYCHA Committee on Program: Minutes, 1934-1935 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - NYCHA: Correspondence, 1934 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - NYCHA: Correspondence, 1935-1936 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - NYCHA: Speeches, 1936 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - NYCHA: Resolutions, 1934 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Vladeck Houses, 1939-1940 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Subseries C: General Material
    - 50th Birthday Jubilee, 1935-1936 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Alderman, 1918 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Biographical Material, 1939-1940 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Bromberg, May Vladeck: Articles by, undated, 1939 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Bromberg, May Vladeck: Correspondence, Jan 1939-Sep 1939 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Bromberg, May Vladeck: Correspondence, Oct 1939-1940 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Bromberg, May Vladeck: Correspondence, 1945, 1955 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Bromberg, May Vladeck: Interview concerning Baruch Charney Vladeck, Nov 13, 1964 (Box 15, Folder 12A)
    - Bromberg, May Vladeck: United Office and Professional Workers Association Materials (including Leonard Bright report on branches), 1938-1939 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Bromberg, May Vladeck: Women's Division, American Labor Party, 1939 (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Business Cards, Undated (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Camp Vacamas, 1938 (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Campaign Material, Oct 1930 (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - City Council, 1937-1938 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Clippings (English and Yiddish), 1911, 1930-1937; 1944 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - College Records, Papers, 1914-1916 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Condolences, 1938 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Condolences: Workmen's Circle, 1938 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Death, 1938-1940 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Election Expenditures, Oct 1937-Nov 1937 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Election Fund, Sep 1937-Dec 1937 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Election Returns, 1937 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Financial, 1921, 1934-1935 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Health, 1938 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Held, Adolph: "Vladeck, On the Tenth Anniversary of His Death" (Australian Jewish Forum, Apr 1949) (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Honors, 1917, 1938 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Jewish Daily Forward, 1929-1936 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Jewish Organizations, 1933-1936 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Passports and Identity Cards, 1918-1937, Undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Poem: "I Know," B.C. Vladek (Australian Jewish Forum, Jul 1947) (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Political Activity, 1933-1935 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Taxes, 1919-1938 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Tsukunft, 1916-1938 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Vladeck, Clara Richman: Correspondence, 1927-1940 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Vladeck, William C. (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Writings: English, 1911, 1934-1935, Undated (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Writings: Yiddish, undated, 1911, 1932-1936 (Box 17, Folder 11)
- Series IV. Photographs
  This series contains over 480 photoprints and offers an in-depth view of both the personal and political life of Baruch Charney Vladeck. Among the pictures included in the initial donation, portraits of Vladeck himself and snapshots of his family make up one-fourth of the collection. Included are albumen prints of Vladeck and his brother in Russia as young men. Photoprints such as the fourth reunion of the Jewish Labor Bund in 1929 and Vladeck with a group of bundist and futurists in Europe emphasize that he maintained his ties with Jewish leftists in Europe. At the same time, the range of his political involvements in America are also documented in these photoprints. Examples include: Vladeck with Mayor La Guardia and other New York City Housing Authority members, Vladeck at an unidentified rally with John Lewis, and David Dubinsky and Vladeck speaking at the 50th Anniversary Dinner of the Jewish Press in America. The collection also includes photoprints of his funeral in 1938 (including those showing Governor Lehman, Mayor La Guardia and Senator Wagner), the dedication of the S.S. Vladeck in 1944, and a group of thirty-two images of Governor Lehman. In 1996 an additional forty-one black and white photographs were donated to the library, ranging in type from 2" x 3" snapshots to 8" x 10" formal portraits. Dates range from the 1920s-1940s. Subjects include Vladeck himself, acquaintances, and housing in the United States, Eastern Europe, and Israel.
  - Portraits, 1903-1939 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Family, 1905-1936 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Family, 1936-1938 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Group scenes in Europe (Medem Sanitarium, futurists, Bundists, School for Young Seamstresses), 1924-1936 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Political Gatherings (Socialist Party, LaGuardia, NYC Housing, Architectural League, Jewish Press in America), 1930-1937 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Vladeck and Colleagues, 1924-1936 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Rolland Theater, Brooklyn, 1928 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Housing (Dutch houses, unidentified housing project), undated (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Travel (California, Gosum Lake, England, Germany), undated (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Travel (Middle East, Jewish Junior and Children's Farm Ben-Shemen), 1938 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous (Cleveland Socialist Sunday School, Abraham Cahan, Ukrainian Jewish Cooperative Loan meeting), 1924 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Funeral, Nov 2, 1938 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Vladeck Exhibition at Central Jewish Library and Archives, 1939 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Camp Tamiment, Vladeck cabin, undated (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - Vladeck City, New York City Housing Authority, 1939-1940 (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - S.S. Vladeck, 1944 (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - Camp Vladeck (near Cleveland), 1946 (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - Friends, undated (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - Unidentified group portraits, undated (Box 18, Folder 19)
  - Herbert Lehman, undated (Box 18, Folder 20)
  - Portraits of Vladeck, undated (Box 18, Folder 21)
  - Events clippings and family slide, 1930s-1964 (Box 18, Folder 22)
  - Clippings (housing demonstration, Vladeck's funeral, banquet of Women's American ORT), 1938 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Memorial (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Portrait - The dear and heartfelt comrade Vladeck, signed Shmenfiln, Jul 12, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Baruch Charney Vladeck - Graphic comprised of Yiddish words with accompanying poem (with English translation), undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Dinner party, tailors school, carpentry school, "Morning Red", 1934 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Farewell Dinner for Herbert Morrison, Hotel Victoria, 1936 (Box Tamiment Shared XOS001, Folder 4)
  - Group portrait, undated (Box Tamiment Shared XOS001, Folder 4)
  - Vladeck Memorial Meeting, Carnegie Hall and program, Dec 11, 1938 (Box Tamiment Shared XOS001, Folder 4)
  - Banquet for 10th Anniversary of uptown branch of the Socialist Party (Box Tamiment Shared XOS001, Folder 4)
  - 25th Anniversary of the Jewish Daily Forward, New York Hippodrome, Apr 23, 1922 (Box Tamiment Shared XOS001, Folder 4)
  - Photos taken in Europe, undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Photos taken in United States, undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Portraits, housing, Israel, Tel Aviv, ACWA convention, Jewish artwork, acquaintances, Camp Tamiment), undated (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Photographs (photographs of documents, convention, clippings from Jewish Daily Forward), undated (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Luncheon for B.C. Vladeck hosted by Jewish Labor Committee, Hotel Commodore, Oct 1, 1936 (Box Tamiment Shared XOS001)
  - Photo album, Medem Sanatorium near Warsaw, presented to BC Vladeck on his visit; loose photos, 1937, 1955 (Box 26)
  - A. Drankov photographs of B.C. Vladeck (Box Tamiment Shared XOS001)
- Series V. Audio Recordings, 1935-1942; 2014.106
  This series primarily consists of recordings created after Baruch Charney Vladeck's death in 1938, including a memorial service broadcast on WEVD Radio in 1942 and a speech given by his daughter to the New York City Housing Authority to celebrate the opening of the Valdeck City Houses in 1940. This series also contains a speech given by Baruch Charney Vladeck to the Workmen's Circle at Madison Square Gardens in 1935.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Materials in this series were originally recorded on seven vinyl audio discs (78 rpm playing speed). Recordings from these discs have been digitized and stored on an access CD. Researchers must use access copies.
  - Irene Vladeck: Con. Housing, Dec 21; 2014.106; 1 item (Box 20, Cd 1, Track 1, Disk 1)
    This recording contains a speech discussing the demolition of tenements in New York City.
  - Workmen's Circle Mr. B Vladeck: Madison Square Garden, May 5, 1935; 2014.106; 2 item (Box 20, Cd 1, Track 2-4, Disk 2-3)
  - Miss Vladeck's Speech, Mar 15, 1940; 2014.106; 1 item (Box 20, Cd 1, Track 5, Disk 4)
    This recording contains a speech by Baruch Vladeck's daughter to the New York City Housing Authority during the opening of the Baruch Charney Vladeck City Houses in 1940.
  - Vladeck Memorial WEVD, Aug 31, 1942; 2014.106; 3 items (Box 20, Disk 5-7, Cd 1, Track 6-11)
- Unprocessed Materials (Box Shared Tamiment 043)